A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Paris Field Office files FA724
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Paris Field Office files
1970-1975
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA724
4.84 Cubic Feet
In July 1975, Marion Bieber, an assistant administrative officer in the Foundation's Paris field office, shipped 15 boxes of Paris field office administrative files to Eldon Jones, Foundation Archivist in New York. In September 1980, Ms. Bieber shipped 21 more boxes of administrative files to Mr. Jones. Of the first group, 7 boxes contained non-Foundation personal records which were sent to the appropriate persons. The remaining 8 boxes were assigned box numbers and stored in the Record Storage Center. Four were given box numbers: 13215, 13218, 13231, 13232. Four were stored and kept with the box numbers assigned to them by the Paris office: 2, 3, 7, 9. The second group were assigned box numbers 11100-11122. • 11100 to 11106 - Subject files • 11107, 11108 - Administrative and General Correspondence files • 11109 to 11111(beg) - General Correspondence files • 11111(end), 11112 - Miscellaneous Subject files • 11113-11122 - Financial files with retention schedules, several loose nonfinancial files and the Paris chrons. The Paris Files contain program-related material and administrative material related to the daily operation of the Field Office.
Conditions Governing Access
Material more than ten years old is open for scholarly research.
Select individual files are restricted, as noted. Permission to access these files must be obtained from the Ford Foundation before scholarly access is permitted.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be restricted from scholarly research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment.
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be restricted from scholarly research at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/RAC Head of Reference.
Office history
The idea of a Ford Foundation field office in Europe was first presented in a December 1967 information paper to the Board of Trustees titled "Planning for the Foundation's Activities in Europe" (#002122). The paper outlined the rationale for a "European" office and cited several advantages to having a presence in Europe.
In the information paper several arguments for opening an office in Europe were forwarded: 1) a desire to strengthen European-North American ties to reflect changes in Cold War thinking; 2) a reexamining of American foreign policy in Europe; 3) a redefining of the United States role in Europe in order to better coordinate cooperation on security and economic matters within the European-Atlantic community. A European office would help facilitate establishing contacts with individuals and institutions in Europe, something which could not be done as effectively from New York. The European office would differ from Ford's other field offices because its primary function would be to act as a liaison between New York and European clients. It would also provide logistical support and coordinate stays for Ford Foundation staff traveling to Europe.
The idea was put aside as economically unviable at the time and was not discussed again for several years. It resurfaced in a March 1969 discussion paper titled "A Foundation Office in Europe" (#009034). The general feeling was that a European office would help to broaden and update an old network of clients and friends which would allow the Foundation to gain a 'European' perspective essential for the Foundation to be able to involve itself in European affairs. In the discussion paper an argument was presented against opening an office so as not to single out Europe for special treatment by the Foundation. A modest, low-key office launched without fanfare was recommended, with a Program Officer from the European and International Affairs (EIA) division, an office manager and one or two secretaries. The office would be under the direction of EIA in New York.
The Foundation believed that opportunities for grant-making would present themselves once the field office was opened. The staff began to establish contacts with prominent European individuals and organizations in order to find prospective grantees.
The Paris field office opened in the summer of 1970 with a staff of two: Marion Bieber, assistant administrative officer, and William Bader, program officer and field office representative. The office was opened for the purposes of:
1) identifying European projects and European partners for international projects that would help to find solutions to "common problems of industrial societies" and 2) identifying European projects as well as persons able to assist developing countries in areas of interest to other divisions of the Foundation in New York and in its overseas offices.
These two purposes were to be fulfilled by the Paris office in different ways:
a) by the development of specific programs in Europe under the auspices and in close collaboration with EIA (New York) and b) by channeling information, ideas and suggestions to other divisions and c) by providing services and facilities to program officers in the U.S. and overseas who wished to develop closer cooperation with Europe in the pursuit of their own programs.
Grants initiated out of the Paris field office for the most part fell into four categories. They were: 1) Arms control, 2) International security and peace research, 3) Migratory labor and migration and 4) The role of parliaments in contemporary European societies.
The Paris field office closed in the summer of 1975 due to budgetary restrictions. At the time of closing, Marion Bieber was administering the field office and David Heaps was the program officer and field office representative in Paris. Grants to organizations in Europe were subsequently administered out of New York ("Some Thoughts After 10 Years of Ford Foundation Work in Europe" by Marion Bieber [#009387]).
Biographical sketches
Biographical sketches of some of the key individuals involved with the Paris field office are listed below.
William Bader: Office Representative of the Paris field office from Summer 1970 to Summer 1974
David Bell: Vice President of the International Affairs division during the entire period that the Paris field office was open
Marion Bieber: Assistant Administrative Officer of the Paris field office from Summer 1970 to closing on June 30, 1975
Ruth Carter: Assistant Administrative Officer of the European and International Affairs program, 1973-1975
Art Cyr: Assistant Program Officer then Program Officer of the European and International Affairs program, 1970-1974
Felice Gaer: Assistant Program Officer and then Program Officer of the European and International Affairs program, 1974-1975
Craufurd Goodwin: Officer-in-Charge of European and International Affairs program during the entire period that the Paris field office was open
David Heaps: Office Representative of the Paris field office after William Bader from Summer 1973 to closing on June 30, 1975
Moselle Kimbler: Assistant Program Officer of the European and International Affairs program, 1970-1972
Andrzej Korbonski: Program Officer of the European and International Affairs program, 1970-1971
Ivo Lederer: Program Officer of the European and International Affairs program, 1970-1975
Peter Ruof: Program Officer of the European and International Affairs program, 1973-1975
Alessandro Silj: Program Officer of the European and International Affairs program, 1970-1972
Francis Sutton: Deputy Vice-President of the International Affairs division during the entire period that the Paris field office was open
Scope and Contents
The Paris field office files contain records generated by the daily operations of the office from 1970 to 1975. The files also contain some items from the late 1960s and as late as 1978.
Arrangement
The Paris Field Office files have been organized into four series:
I. Subject Files II. Administrative Office Files III. General Correspondence IV. Chronological Correspondence
Arrangement within each series corresponds as closely as possible to the original order established by the Paris office.
Separated Materials
Staff and consultant reports were removed from the files and accessioned as part of the Archives collection of staff and consultant reports. Their locations have been noted on cross-reference sheets within the files. A list of all cataloged reports is in Appendix A of the register. Reports not related to Ford Foundation activities have been discarded.
Ford Foundation
- Subject Files, I
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Subject Files, contains correspondence, memoranda, and reports to and from grantees, prospective grantees and organizations with which the Paris field office had significant contact. It also contains correspondence between the Foundation in New York and its field office in Paris. Most grant material has been removed from these files and can be found in the appropriate grant files. Cross-references were inserted to identify weeded grant material.
  It is suggested that folders out of which grant material has been removed be used to supplement the grant files and be viewed in conjunction with their respective grant files. Also note that several of the subject files are topical and do not relate to a specific organization, e.g. Vietnam, arms control, urbanization.
  Arrangement
  Series I is arranged alphabetically by name of organization (and occasional topical subject, e.g. Arms Control). The subject files were organized into two subseries which both run alphabetically from A to Z. This was done because further boxes were discovered after processing had begun. Comingling the series would have caused confusion because numbered folders would not correspond with alphabetical listings.
  Some files do not fall correctly in the alphabetical sequence. For example, many university subject files are found under 'U' instead of under their university name, e.g. Yale University.
  - Subseries A, A
    - African Studies in French Universities, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Arms Control and Disarmament Agency, 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - American Academy of Arts & Sciences, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - American Council of Young Political Leaders, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - American Library in Paris, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - American Society of International Law, 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Arms Control: General, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Atlantic Institute, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Baulieu, Etienne of Hôpital Kremlin-Bicêtre, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - British Inst. of Intl. & Comparative Law, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Brookings Institution, 1971-1974 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Carnegie Endowment for International Peace, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - CEDAF (Centre d'Etudes et de Documentation Africaines), 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - CENSIS (Center for Research on Social Investments), 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Centre for Environmental Studies - London, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Schaff Institute, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - CEDEP (Centre Européen d'Education Permanente), 1974 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Centre de Recherche sur la Décision, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Catholic Institute for Intl. Relations, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - College of Europe, 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Common Problems Research Competition, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - COPRED (Consortium on Peace Education and Development), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - COSPOS (Bi-National Committee for Social and Political Sciences), 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Council for European Studies, 1971-1975 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Council on Foreign Relations, 1970-1975 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Deutsche Entwicklungshilfe fur Soziales Wohnungs, 1970-1971 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Deutsche Gessellschaft fur Friedens und Konflictforschung, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Educational Technology in European Higher Education - Grenoble Conf. - 9/24-27/74, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Energy Policy Project, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - EURNAC (European-North American Committee), 1971-1974 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - European Association of Development Centers and Institutes, 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - European Libraries and Institutes, 1970-1974 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Federal Trust for Education & Research, 1970-1974 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Fédération Nationale des Ecoles, des Parents et des Educateurs, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - FAP - Common Problems (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Finland - Helsinki Meeting (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Finnish Institutes (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Fondation pour le Dévelopement Culturel, 1970-1974 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Fondation FACIM, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Fondation Royaumont, 1971-1975 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - The Wates Foundation, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Fundacion General Mediterranea, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - France, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - German-American Conferences, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - German Comm. on Economic and Social Change, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - American German Journalist Conference, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Humanities and the Arts Projects, 1970-1973 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - INODEP (Institute Cumenique Pour le Developpement des Peuples), 1974 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Institute de la Communauté Européenne pour les Etudes Universitaires, 1970-1975 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Institut Francais d'Histoire Sociale, 1971-1974 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Institut National Agronomique, 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Institut Universitaire des Hautes Etudes Internationales, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Institute of Advanced Legal Studies, 1970-1974 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Aspen Institute, 1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - International Affairs Institute - Italy, 1970-1974 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Institute of Race Relations (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Adlai Stevenson Institute of Intl. Affairs (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Institute for the Study of Conflict, 1970-1975 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Inter-Nation Television Trust (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Pierre Emmanuel - IACF (See Folder 61) (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Intl. Association of Cultural Freedom (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - International Broadcast Institute (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Intl. Institute of Administrative Sciences, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - International Institute for Labor Studies, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Intl. Institute for Strategic Studies, 1970-1974 (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - Intl. Planned Parenthood Federation, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - International P.E.N., 1972 (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - International Press Institute - Zurich, 1971-1974 (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - International Red Cross, 1972-1974 (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - IREX (Int'l Research and Exchanges Board), 1971-1973 (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - International Social Security Association, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - International Social Science Council, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - Interphil, 1971-1974 (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - ISSOCO (Instituto per lo Studio Della Societa Contemporanea), 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - Italian Pugwash Group - ISODARCO, 1971-1974 (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - Jeune Afrique - Claude Labbé (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - London Business School, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - London School of Economics, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 78)
    - Management Education in Europe, 1970-1974 (Box 3, Folder 79)
    - Manchester Business School (Box 3, Folder 80)
    - Medico-Social Research Board - Dublin (Box 3, Folder 81)
    - M.I.T. - European Security Project (Box 3, Folder 82)
    - Mouvement Francais pour le Planning Familial (Box 3, Folder 83)
    - Norwegian Institute of Intl. Affairs (Box 3, Folder 84)
    - Nuffield College (Box 3, Folder 85)
    - Overseas Development Council (Box 3, Folder 86)
    - Overseas Development Institute (Box 3, Folder 87)
    - Political and Economic Planning, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 88)
    - Population, 1971-1973 (Box 3, Folder 89)
    - Population Council, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 90)
    - Queens College, 1971-1972 (Box 4, Folder 91)
    - Royal College of Art, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 92)
    - Rumanian Urban Studies, 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 93)
    - Schwartz, Bertrand, 1970-1973 (Box 4, Folder 94)
    - SIDA (Swedish Intl. Development Authority), 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 95)
    - Social Science Research Council - NY, 1974-1975 (Box 4, Folder 96)
    - Société des Amis de Léon Blum, 1970-1974 (Box 4, Folder 97)
    - Société Protectice des Humains, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 98)
    - Soviet and E. European Research Competition, 1974-1975 (Box 4, Folder 99)
    - SIPRI (Stockholm Intl. Peace Research Inst.), 1970-1975 (Box 4, Folder 100)
    - Strategic Concepts of Arms Control, 1970-1973 (Box 4, Folder 101)
    - Swedish Institutes, 1971-1973 (Box 4, Folder 102)
    - Telecommunications Task Force, 1972-1974 (Box 4, Folder 103)
    - Trade Policy Research Centre, 1970-1974 (Box 4, Folder 104)
    - 2-Key Projects (Box 4, Folder 105)
    - Travel and Study Awards, 1970-1975 (Box 4, Folder 106)
    - United Nations Association, 1970-1974 (Box 4, Folder 107)
    - Universities in U.S.A., 1971-1974 (Box 4, Folder 108)
    - Universities Services Center, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 109)
    - Columbia University, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 110)
    - Cornell University, 1971-1974 (Box 4, Folder 111)
    - Duke University, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 112)
    - Granada University, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 113)
    - Harvard University, 1971-1974 (Box 4, Folder 114)
    - Johns Hopkins University, 1971-1974 (Box 5, Folder 115)
    - McGill University, 1970-1973 (Box 5, Folder 116)
    - Michigan University (Box 5, Folder 117)
    - Princeton University, 1971-1974 (Box 5, Folder 118)
    - Queen's University, 1973-1974 (Box 5, Folder 119)
    - University of Surrey, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 120)
    - University of Toronto, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 121)
    - Tufts University, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 122)
    - University of Virginia, 1970-1973 (Box 5, Folder 123)
    - Yale University, 1970-1974 (Box 5, Folder 124)
    - Urbanization (Box 5, Folder 125)
    - U.S.S.R., 1971-1973 (Box 5, Folder 126)
    - Vietnam, 1973-1974 (Box 5, Folder 127)
    - West European Fellowship Program, 1970-1974 (Box 5, Folder 128)
    - Benoit Verhaegen, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 129)
    - Wilton Park, 1970-1974 (Box 5, Folder 130)
    - Woodrow Wilson Intl. Center for Scholars, 1971-1974 (Box 5, Folder 131)
    - Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution, 1970-1973 (Box 5, Folder 132)
    - World Assembly of Youth, 1970-1971 (Box 5, Folder 133)
    - World Law Fund, 1971-1972 (Box 5, Folder 134)
  - Subseries B, B
    - Amnesty International, 1970-1974 (Box 5, Folder 135)
    - Battelle Institute, 1973-1974 (Box 5, Folder 136)
    - Centre Charles Richet, 1972-1974 (Box 5, Folder 137)
    - Centre for Mediterranean Studies, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 138)
    - Centre de Recherces Historique, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 139)
    - Centre de Sociologie des Organisations, 1971-1974 (Box 5, Folder 140)
    - Ditchley Foundation, 1971-1972 (Box 5, Folder 141)
    - East-West Workshops, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 142)
    - European Economic Commission, 1973-1974 (Box 5, Folder 143)
    - Ecole Pratique des Hautes Etudes, 1973-1974 (Box 5, Folder 144)
    - Fondation Simone et Cino del Duca, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 145)
    - Fondation Européene de la Culture, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 146)
    - Fondation de France, 1972 (Box 5, Folder 147)
    - Association des Amis de Lourmarin, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 148)
    - Gulbenkian Foundation, 1971-1973 (Box 6, Folder 149)
    - George Marshall Memorial Fund, 1971-1974 (Box 6, Folder 150)
    - Thyssen Foundation, 1971-1974 (Box 6, Folder 151)
    - Fondation Paul-Henri Spaak, 1972-1973 (Box 6, Folder 152)
    - Foundation Stifterverband, 1971-1972 (Box 6, Folder 153)
    - Volkswagen (Foundation), 1971-1975 (Box 6, Folder 154)
    - IDERIC (Institut d'Etudes et de Recherches Interethniques et Interculturelles), 1972-1977 (Box 6, Folder 155)
    - International Studies Conference, 1975-1976 (Box 6, Folder 156)
    - Maison des Sciences de l'Homme, 1974-1976 (Box 6, Folder 157)
    - Returning Migrants, 1976-1977 (Box 6, Folder 158)
    - Paris Meeting on Migratory Labor, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 159)
    - European Center for Social Research and Welfare Training - Vienna, 1974-1977 (Box 6, Folder 160)
    - Office de la Radio, Television Francais, 1971-1975 (Box 6, Folder 161)
    - Organization for Economics Cooperation and Development, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 162)
    - Université Catholique de Louvain, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 163)
    - Stanford University, 1971-1973 (Box 6, Folder 164)
    - University of Sussex, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 165)
    - Women in Management, 1975-1976 (Box 6, Folder 166)
    - Women: Task Force on the Status of Women, 1972-1975 (Box 6, Folder 167)
    - Women: Int'l Federation of University Women, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 168)
    - Women: Lucy Cavendish College, 1973-1974 (Box 6, Folder 169)
    - Parliamentary Crisis Research, 1971-1973 (Box 6, Folder 170)
    - Human Rights, 1971-1975 (Box 6, Folder 171)
- Administrative Office Files, II
  Series II, Administrative Office Files, contains correspondence, memoranda and reports distributed between program officers, field offices, and other divisions of the Foundation with which the Paris office had contact.
  Series II is arranged alphabetically by program officer or location of field office. These files have been kept as they were filed by the Paris field office.
  - EIA - European Conference, Sterling Forest, 1971 January (Box 7, Folder 172)
  - EIA - Budget Program and Management (Box 7, Folder 173)
  - EIA - Policy Memoranda (Box 7, Folder 174)
  - EIA - Program Memoranda (Box 7, Folder 175)
  - Board of Trustees, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 176)
  - Bundy, McGeorge (Box 7, Folder 177)
  - Goodwin, Craufurd (Box 7, Folder 178)
  - Lederer, Ivo (Box 7, Folder 179)
  - May, Edgar (Consultant) (Box 7, Folder 180)
  - Silj, Alessandro (Box 7, Folder 181)
  - Staples, Eugene (Box 7, Folder 182)
  - Sutton, Francis (Box 7, Folder 183)
  - Ward, F. Champion (Box 7, Folder 184)
  - Middle East and Africa (MEA) (Box 7, Folder 185)
  - F.O. - Ankara (Box 7, Folder 186)
  - F.O. - Athens (Box 7, Folder 187)
  - F.O. - Beirut (Box 7, Folder 188)
  - F.O. - Dacca (Box 7, Folder 189)
  - F.O. - Lagos (Box 7, Folder 190)
  - F.O. - Mexico (Box 7, Folder 191)
  - F.O. - Tunis (Box 7, Folder 192)
- General Correspondence, III
  Series III, General Correspondence, focuses primarily on prospective grantees and contains correspondence between the Paris office and these organizations and individuals. It provides a good overview of the types of organizations and individuals of interest to the field office.
  Much of the contents in this series relates to the subjects of greatest interest to the Paris office. The four main areas of interest to the Foundation in Europe were: arms control, international security issues and peace research, migration and migratory labor, and the role of parliaments in contemporary European society.
  Series III is arranged alphabetically by name.
  - General - "A" (Box 7, Folder 193)
  - General - "B" (Box 7, Folder 194)
  - General - "C" (Box 7, Folder 195)
  - General - "D" (Box 7, Folder 196)
  - General - "E" (Box 8, Folder 197)
  - General - "F" (Box 8, Folder 198)
  - General - "G" (Box 8, Folder 199)